<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<header>
	<docType>ESR Contribution</docType>
	<indicatorShortName>structural_epifauna</indicatorShortName>
	<indicatorTitle>Eastern and Northern Bering Sea – Structural Epifauna</indicatorTitle>
	<indicatorRegion>EBS</indicatorRegion>
	<authors>Thaddaeus Buser and Sean Rohan</authors>
	<contactEmail>thaddaeus.buser@noaa.gov</contactEmail>
	<authorAffiliations>Resource Assessment and Conservation Engineering Division, Alaska Fisheries Science Center National Marine Fisheries Service, NOAA</authorAffiliations>
	<lastUpdate>September 2024</lastUpdate>
</header>
<body>
	<indicatorDescription>
	Groups considered to be structural epifauna include: sea pens, corals, anemones, and sponges. Corals are rarely encountered in the eastern or northern Bering Sea so they were not included here; sea pens are rarely encountered in the northern Bering Sea so they are only shown for the eastern Bering Sea shelf survey. Relative CPUE by weight (kg per hectare) was calculated and plotted for each species group by year for 1982–2023 for the eastern Bering Sea survey and for 2010–2023 for the northern Bering Sea survey. Catch methods for the northern Bering Sea were standardized in 2010, so the catches from previous years do not provide comparable data and are excluded. Relative CPUE was calculated by setting the largest biomass in the time series to a value of 1 and scaling other annual values proportionally. The standard error (±1) was weighted proportionally to the CPUE to produce a relative standard error.</indicatorDescription>
	<methodologicalChanges>
Methods for producing this indicator have been updated this year to account for process error in survey abundance estimates, facilitate interpretation of indicator trends, utilize consistent statistical methods across ESR regions, and ensure consistent species group composition across regions. Previously, time series for this indicator were calculated as the average bottom trawl survey catch-per-unit effort for the full survey area (CPUE, kg ha) that were scaled proportionally to the maximum CPUE in the bottom trawl survey time series.

This year, stratum biomass estimates were calculated using the _gapindex_ R package [@gapindex], which uses the Wakabayashi et al. (1985) method to estimate design-based abundance index means and coefficients of variation (CVs) from catch (kg) and effort data (area swept; ha) collected during EBS and NBS summer bottom trawl surveys. Then, abundance index time series means and confidence intervals were estimated by fitting a multivariate random effects model (REM) to stratum biomass estimates and CVs using the R package _rema_ [@rema; @Sullivan2022] to account for process error in indicator time series. The code and methods to calculate abundance indices and fit REM to time series are implemented in the R package _esrindex_ [@esrindex].

In this update, we also provide figures showing REM estimates of abundance, by stratum, to improve the characterization of spatial abundance patterns and trends, similar to subarea trends that have been presented in the AI and GOA ESRs.

Switching to REM addresses an issue raised during the November 2023 BSAI Groundfish Plan Team meeting pertaining to statistical methods to estimate Structural Epifauna abundance in the EBS:

_“The Team had a conversation about utilizing random effects models to deal with process error in the indicator and standardizing the index for variables such as bottom contact time.”_

We note that bottom contact time is already accounted for in bottom trawl survey effort data because effort is only calculated for the time the net is on bottom based on bottom contact sensor data.
	</methodologicalChanges>
	<statusAndTrends>


	_Eastern Bering Sea:_ 

	As in 2022, the relative catch rates for sea anemones (Actiniaria) were similar to those observed during 2010–2015, compared to lower catch rates observed from 2016–2021. Likewise, sea pen (Pennatulacea) estimates for 2023 are similar to those observed in 2021 and 2022, which together represent an increase from 2019 observations and a return to a catch rate similar to that observed 1999–2005 and 2013–2016. The catch rate of sponges (Porifera) in 2023 continues the very low catch level observed since 2021, which was the lowest level observed in the time series, but similar to results observed intermittently during the early years of the time series, 1984–1992. These trends should be viewed with caution because the consistency and quality of their enumeration have varied over the time series [@Stevenson2009; @Stevensonetal2016]. Moreover, the identifcation of trends is uncertain given the large variability in relative CPUE (Figure 38). 

	_Northern Bering Sea:_ 

	The relative catch rates of sea anemones are consistent across the time series except for 2022, which was much larger than all other years. This difers slightly from the trend observed in the eastern Bering Sea from 2010–2023, which showed relatively high catch rates from 2010–2013 and 2022–2023, with relatively low catch rates in between. The catch rate of sponges in the NBS is highly variable across the time series, with high relative catch rates 2010, 2017, 2022, and 2023 and low catch rates in 2019 and 2021 (Figure 39).
	</statusAndTrends>
	<factorsInfluencingTrends>It is difficult to identify trends, given that the NBS survey has been conducted intermittently and only recently (i.e., starting in 2017) been conducted on a more regular schedule. Further research in several areas would beneft the interpretation of structural epifauna trends including systematics and taxonomy of Bering Sea shelf invertebrates, survey gear selectivity, and the life history characteristics of the epibenthic organisms captured by the survey trawl.</factorsInfluencingTrends>

	<implications>Understanding the trends as well as the distribution patterns of structural epifauna is important for modeling habitat to develop spatial management plans for protecting habitat, understanding fishing gear impacts, and predicting responses to future climate change [@Rooper2016]. More research on the eastern Bering Sea shelf will be needed to determine if there are defnitive links.</implications>
	<researchPriorities>NA</researchPriorities>
</body>
<figures>
	<fig>
		<figureNumber>1</figureNumber>
		<figurePath>EBS_rema_structural_epifauna_full_region_ze.png</figurePath>
		<figureCaption>Biomass index of Structural Epifauna (sponges, sea anemones, and sea pens) from AFSC/RACE summer bottom trawl surveys of the eastern Bering Sea from 1982 to 2024.  Panels show the observed total survey biomass (blue points), standard error (vertical error bars), biomass index time series mean (solid black line), 95% confidence interval (gray shading), overall time series mean (solid gray line), and horizontal lines representing one and two standard deviations from the mean, respectively.</figureCaption>
	</fig>
	<fig>
		<figureNumber>2</figureNumber>
		<figurePath>EBS_rema_structural_epifauna_subarea_bar.png</figurePath>
		<figureCaption>Biomass index of Structural Epifauna (sponges, sea anemones, and sea pens) in eastern Bering Sea survey strata (10-60) estimated from AFSC/RACE summer bottom trawl survey data from 1982 to 2024.</figureCaption>
	</fig>
	<fig>
		<figureNumber>3</figureNumber>
		<figurePath>NBS_rema_structural_epifauna_full_region_ze.png</figurePath>
		<figureCaption>Biomass index of Structural Epifauna (sponges, sea anemones, and Pennatulaceans) from AFSC/RACE summer bottom trawl surveys of the northern Bering Sea from 2010 to 2023. Panels show the observed total survey biomass (blue points), standard error (vertical error bars), biomass index time series mean (solid black line), 95% confidence interval (gray shading), overall time series mean (solid gray line), and horizontal lines representing one and two standard deviations from the mean, respectively. </figureCaption>
	</fig>
</figures>
