<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<header>
	<docType>ESR Contribution</docType>
	<indicatorShortName>misc_species</indicatorShortName>
	<indicatorTitle>Miscellaneous benthic fauna—Gulf of Alaska Bottom Trawl Survey</indicatorTitle>
	<indicatorRegion>GOA</indicatorRegion>
	<authors>Sarah Friedman</authors>
	<contactEmail>Sarah.Friedman@noaa.gov</contactEmail>
	<authorAffiliations>Resource Assessment and Conservation Engineering Division, Alaska Fisheries Science Center, NOAA Fisheries</authorAffiliations>
	<lastUpdate>September 2025</lastUpdate>
</header>
<body>
	<indicatorDescription>
Benthic species are often reliable ecosystem indicators due to their sensitivity to environmental fluctuations [@Tampo2021] and their integral role in marine food webs [@Griffiths2017]. Thus, changes in their abundance are widely used as sentinels for shifts in environmental conditions and ecosystem functioning [@Salas2006; @Jayachandran2022]. The benthic fauna presented here are categorized into four taxonomic groups: eelpouts (family Zoarcidae), poachers (family Agonidae), shrimps (infraorder Caridea), and sea stars (class Asteroidea). The three species comprising the bulk of the eelpout group are the ebony eelpout (_Lycodes concolor_), bicolor eelpout (_L. beringi_) and, to a lesser extent, the shortfin eelpout (_L. brevipes_). The biomass of poachers is dominated by sturgeon poachers (_Podothecus accipenserinus_) and sawback poachers (_Sarritor frenatus_). The biomass of shrimps is largely composed of Alaskan pink shrimp (_Pandalus eous_) and yellowleg pandalids (_P. tridens_), whereas the biomass of sea stars are primarily comprised of _Henricia_ stars and the fragile sea star (_Cheiraster dawsoni_). These benthic fauna, when considered alongside formally assessed and commercially targeted species, can provide valuable context for the overall status of the Gulf of Alaska (GOA) ecosystem. Since 1990, the biennial RACE Groundfish Assessment Program fishery-independent summer bottom trawl survey in the Gulf of Alaska has deployed the same standardized trawl gear (footrope and trawl net) across the survey region. Therefore, biomass index trends are likely to reflect changes in the abundance of species and life history stages that are available to the survey, especially if trends are sustained over time. 
	
Regional and subarea (NMFS statistical areas 610, 620, 630, 640, 650) indices of abundance (biomass in kilotons) and confidence intervals were estimated for each taxonomic group by fitting a multivariate random effects model (REM) to subarea design-based index of abundance time series that were calculated from RACE Groundfish Assessment Program (GAP) summer bottom trawl survey catch and effort data. Indices were calculated for the entire standardized survey time series (1990 to 2025). Design-based indices of abundance were calculated using the _gapindex_ R package [@gapindex] and REM were fitted to the time series using the _rema_ R package [@rema]. Code and data used to produce these indicators are provided in the _esrindex_ R package and repository [@esrindex].
	</indicatorDescription>
	<methodologicalChanges>Methods for calculating this indicator have been updated for this year, as described in the Gulf of Alaska Structural Epifauna contribution (Conrath, this year's ESR).</methodologicalChanges>
	<statusAndTrends>Echinoderms and shrimp are relatively commonly caught in our survey catches, while eelpouts and poachers occur with less frequency (Figure 82). Echinoderm biomass has been highest in the Chirikof and Kodiak districts historically and appears to be increasing in the latter in recent surveys; this group of benthic invertebrates is common in trawl catches throughout the Gulf. Shrimp biomass has also historically been higher in the Chirikof and Kodiak districts than elsewhere in the Gulf, but appears to be declining in those two districts in recent surveys. Eelpouts occur episodically in catches throughout the GOA, but seem to be more abundant in the Yakutat district where their biomass may be increasing over the time series. Poachers are more common in the Shumagin district than elsewhere in the Gulf where they are uncommon and their highest biomass has historically occurred in the Shumagin and Kodiak districts.</statusAndTrends>
	<factorsInfluencingTrends>Unknown</factorsInfluencingTrends>
	<implications>It is difficult to discern a consistent pattern of biomass or prevalence across these taxonomic groups. There are some patterns within groups (e.g., echinoderms are common throughout the Gulf, eelpout biomass has cycled between highs and lows over the course of the time series and in most districts). Directed research into the population ecology of these taxonomic groups could help to elucidate relationships between their population status and the health of the region.</implications>
	<researchPriorities>NA</researchPriorities>
</body>
<figures>
	<fig>
		<figureNumber>1</figureNumber>
		<figurePath>GOA_rema_misc_species_full_region_ze.png</figurePath>
		<figureCaption>Biomass index (kilotons) of miscellaneous benthic fauna (eelpouts, poachers, shrimps, sea stars) from RACE Groundfish Assessment Program summer bottom trawl surveys of the Gulf of Alaska from 1990 to 2025. Panels show the observed survey biomass index mean (blue points), random effects model fitted mean (solid black line), 95% confidence interval (gray shading), overall time series mean (solid gray line), and horizontal dashed gray lines representing one standard deviation from the time series mean.</figureCaption>
	</fig>
	<fig>
		<figureNumber>2</figureNumber>
		<figurePath>GOA_rema_misc_species_subarea_bar.png</figurePath>
		<figureCaption>Biomass index (kilotons) of miscellaneous benthic fauna (eelpouts, poachers, shrimps, sea stars) in NMFS Statistical Areas in the Gulf of Alaska (610 - Shumagin, 620 - Chirikof, 630 - Kodiak, 640 - West Yakutat, 650 - Southeast Outside) estimated from RACE Groundfish Assessment Program summer bottom trawl survey data from 1990 to 2025. Colors denote NMFS statistical areas.</figureCaption>
	</fig>
</figures>
