<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<header>
	<docType>ESR Contribution</docType>
	<indicatorShortName>structural_epifauna</indicatorShortName>
	<indicatorTitle>Structural Epifauna—Gulf of Alaska</indicatorTitle>
	<indicatorRegion>GOA</indicatorRegion>
	<authors>Christina Conrath</authors>
	<contactEmail>Christina.Conrath@noaa.gov</contactEmail>
	<authorAffiliations>Resource Assessment and Conservation Engineering Division, Alaska Fisheries Science Center, NOAA Fisheries</authorAffiliations>
	<lastUpdate>September 2025</lastUpdate>
</header>
<body>
	<indicatorDescription>Structural epifauna groups considered to be Habitat Area of Particular Concern (HAPC) biota include sponges, corals (both hard and soft), and anemones. NOAA Alaska Fisheries’ Resource Assessment and Conservation Engineering Division’s Groundfish Assessment Program (RACE/GAP) fishery-independent summer bottom trawl surveys in the Gulf of Alaska (GOA) are designed to assess populations of commercially and ecologically important fishes and invertebrates. Since 1990, we have deployed the same standardized trawl gear (footrope and trawl net) as is presently in use in the GOA bottom trawl survey. Epifaunal groups like sponges, corals (both hard and soft), pennatulaceans, and anemones form benthic structure that can be part of the communities that make up Habitat Areas of Particular Concern (HAPC). A HAPC is a specific area designation for a type of habitat that plays an important role in a species’ life cycle, or that is sensitive, rare, or vulnerable. 
	
Regional and subarea (NMFS statistical areas 610, 620, 630, 640, 650) indices of abundance (biomass in kilotons) and confidence intervals were estimated for each taxonomic group by fitting a multivariate random effects model (REM) to subarea design-based index of abundance time series that were calculated from RACE Groundfish Assessment Program (GAP) summer bottom trawl survey catch and effort data. Indices were calculated for the entire standardized survey time series (1990 to 2025). Design-based indices of abundance were calculated using the _gapindex_ R package [@gapindex] and REM were fitted to the time series using the _rema_ R package [@rema]. Code and data used to produce these indicators are provided in the _esrindex_ R package and repository [@esrindex].
</indicatorDescription>
	<methodologicalChanges>
Methods for producing this indicator have been updated this year to account for process error in survey abundance estimates, facilitate interpretation of indicator trends, utilize consistent statistical methods across ESR regions, and ensure consistent species group composition across regions. Previously, two time series were presented for each species group: (1) average bottom trawl survey catch-per-unit effort for within International North Pacific Fisheries Commission (INPFC) subareas (CPUE, kg ha^-1^) that were scaled proportionally to the maximum CPUE in the bottom trawl survey time series, and (2) frequency of occurrence of each species group among bottom trawl survey hauls within INPFC subareas.

This year, subarea biomass estimates were calculated using the _gapindex_ R package [@gapindex], which uses the @Wakabayashi1985 method to estimate design-based abundance index means and coefficients of variation (CVs) from catch (kg) and effort data (area swept; ha) collected during Aleutian Islands summer bottom trawl surveys. Then, abundance index time series means and confidence intervals were estimated by fitting a multivariate random effects model (REM) to NMFS statistical area biomass estimates and CVs using the R package _rema_ [@Sullivan2022; @rema] to account for process error in indicator time series. This estimation method was implemented for eastern Bering Sea and Aleutian Islands ESRs in 2024. The transition from reporting biomass by INPFC subarea to NMFS statistical area reflects a restratification of the Gulf of Alaska survey in which bottom trawl survey stratum boundaries align with NMFS statistical area boundaries [@Oyafuso2022]. The code and methods to calculate abundance indices and fit REM to time series are implemented in the R package _esrindex_ [@esrindex].

Switching to REM addresses an issue raised during the November 2023 BSAI Groundfish Plan Team meeting pertaining to statistical methods to estimate Structural Epifauna abundance:

“The Team had a conversation about utilizing random effects models to deal with process error in the indicator and standardizing the index for variables such as bottom contact time.”

We note that bottom contact time is already accounted for in bottom trawl survey effort data because effort is only calculated for the time the net is on bottom based on bottom contact sensor data.
</methodologicalChanges>
	<statusAndTrends>A few general patterns are discernible among the epifaunal groups summarized here (Figure 24). Sponges are prevalent in bottom trawl survey hauls throughout the Gulf of Alaska (GOA), occurring in 40–50% of catches in all districts sampled, though their abundance appears to be declining in recent years in at least the Shumagin and Kodiak districts. Sea anemones appear to be more abundant in the western GOA though they are relatively common across the survey area, occurring in 40–50% of trawl catches much of the time. Gorgonian corals are most abundant in southeast Alaska, contrasting with the pattern of abundance observed with sponges and anemones, and are not common in our trawl catches, even where their abundance is higher. The sea pens and sea whips (Pennatulacea) are neither common nor abundant in GOA trawl catches though we have episodically caught them in high abundance in the Chirikof district. Hydrocorals are not abundant or common in the GOA either, though historically they have been caught in higher abundance in the Shumagin district of the western Gulf.</statusAndTrends>
	<factorsInfluencingTrends>The Gulf of Alaska Bottom Trawl Survey does not sample any of these fauna well, so some caution is recommended in interpreting these trends in CPUE and abundance indices.</factorsInfluencingTrends>
	<implications>Population trends for these epifaunal groups across the GOA may reflect changes in their habitats or environment. Recent climatic events like the Warm Blob [@Bond2015; @DiLorenzo2016] have almost certainly impacted some of these sessile populations. Continued monitoring and further studies to better understand the mechanisms and implications of observed trends are key to a better understanding of the ecosystem.</implications>
	<researchPriorities>NA</researchPriorities>
</body>
<figures>
	<fig>
		<figureNumber>1</figureNumber>
		<figurePath>GOA_rema_structural_epifauna_full_region_ze.png</figurePath>
		<figureCaption>Biomass index of structural epifauna (sponges, sea anemones, corals, and Pennatulaceans) from AFSC/RACE summer bottom trawl surveys of the Gulf of Alaska from 1990 to 2025. Panels show the observed total survey biomass (blue points), standard error (vertical error bars), biomass index time series mean (solid black line), 95% confidence interval (gray shading), overall time series mean (solid gray line), and horizontal lines representing one and two standard deviations from the mean, respectively.</figureCaption>
	</fig>
	<fig>
		<figureNumber>2</figureNumber>
		<figurePath>GOA_rema_structural_epifauna_subarea_bar.png</figurePath>
		<figureCaption>Biomass index of structural epifauna (sponges, sea anemones, corals, and Pennatulaceans) in NMFS Statistical Areas in the Gulf of Alaska (610 - Shumagin, 620 - Chirikof, 630 - Kodiak, 640 - West Yakutat, 650 - Southeast Outside) estimated from RACE Groundfish Assessment Program summer bottom trawl survey data from 1990 to 2025. Colors denote NMFS statistical areas.</figureCaption>
	</fig>
</figures>
