<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<header>
	<docType>ESR Contribution</docType>
	<indicatorShortName>jellyfish</indicatorShortName>
	<indicatorTitle>Jellyfish—Gulf of Alaska Bottom Trawl Survey</indicatorTitle>
	<indicatorRegion>GOA</indicatorRegion>
	<authors>Alexandra Dowlin</authors>
	<contactEmail>Alexandra.Dowlin@noaa.gov</contactEmail>
	<authorAffiliations>Resource Assessment and Conservation Engineering Division, Alaska Fisheries Science Center, NOAA Fisheries</authorAffiliations>
	<lastUpdate>September 2025</lastUpdate>
</header>
<body>
	<indicatorDescription>Jellyfish are an important component of plankton communities and an active area of research at the Alaska Fisheries Science Center (AFSC). Jellyfish act as both predators and competitors of fish, especially early life history stages [@Purcell2001]. Thus, fluctuations in jellyfish abundance may affect ecosystem dynamics and fish abundance through indirect (e.g., competition for prey) and direct (e.g., predation) competition with forage fishes and other commercially and ecologically important species.

Since 1991, the Resource Assessment and Conservation Engineering Division’s Groundfish Assessment Program (RACE-GAP) at AFSC has employed standardized operating procedures in the Aleutian Islands (AI) to deploy the same gear (footrope and bottom trawl net) on triennial (1991-2000) and then biennial (2002-present) bottom trawl surveys. Therefore, biomass index trends are likely to reflect changes in the abundance of species and life history stages that are available to the survey, especially if trends are sustained over time and the relative abundance of jellies from these surveys may be informative of their population trends within the ecosystem (e.g., @Decker2023). 

Regional and subarea (NMFS statistical areas 610, 620, 630, 640, 650) indices of abundance (biomass in kilotons) and confidence intervals were estimated for each taxonomic group by fitting a multivariate random effects model (REM) to subarea design-based index of abundance time series that were calculated from RACE Groundfish Assessment Program (GAP) summer bottom trawl survey catch and effort data. Indices were calculated for the entire standardized survey time series (1990 to 2025). Design-based indices of abundance were calculated using the _gapindex_ R package [@gapindex] and REM were fitted to the time series using the _rema_ R package [@rema]. Code and data used to produce these indicators are provided in the _esrindex_ R package and repository [@esrindex].</indicatorDescription>
	<methodologicalChanges>Methods for calculating this indicator have been updated for this year, as described in the Gulf of Alaska Structural Epifauna contribution (Conrath, this year's ESR).</methodologicalChanges>
	<statusAndTrends>In much of the GOA, relative sea jelly biomass continues to decline from it’s recent high in 2019 with southeast Alaska as a potential exception to this rule (Figure 48). Sea jelly prevalence in trawl catches increases from west to east across the GOA with prevalence in recent surveys declining in the western GOA survey districts of the Shumagins and Chrikof, increasing in the central survey districts of Kodiak and Yakutat, and remaining fairly stable and high in southeast Alaska.</statusAndTrends>
	<factorsInfluencingTrends>Unknown</factorsInfluencingTrends>
	<implications>The primary habitat for these animals is open water and, therefore, the observed patterns of abundance and prevalence could reflect differing oceanographic conditions across the GOA survey area. Alternatively, the observed patterns could reflect that the spatial and temporal progression of the bottom trawl survey that begins in the western GOA in May and moves eastward during the summer until the survey is completed in August in southeast Alaska. More directed study of the ecology and biology of the species in this group is needed to develop a mechanistic understanding of their distribution and abundance patterns.</implications>
	<researchPriorities>NA</researchPriorities>
</body>
<figures>
	<fig>
		<figureNumber>1</figureNumber>
		<figurePath>GOA_rema_jellyfish_full_region_ze.png</figurePath>
		<figureCaption>Biomass index (kilotons) of jellyfish from RACE Groundfish Assessment Program summer bottom trawl surveys of the Gulf of Alaska from 1990 to 2025 showing the observed survey biomass index mean (blue points), random effects model fitted mean (solid black line), 95% confidence interval (gray shading), overall time series mean (solid gray line), and horizontal dashed gray lines representing one standard deviation from the mean.</figureCaption>
		</fig>
		<fig>
		<figureNumber>2</figureNumber>
		<figurePath>GOA_rema_jellyfish_subarea_bar.png</figurePath>
		<figureCaption>Biomass index (kilotons) of jellyfish in NMFS Statistical Areas in the Gulf of Alaska (610 - Shumagin, 620 - Chirikof, 630 - Kodiak, 640 - West Yakutat, 650 - Southeast Outside) estimated from RACE Groundfish Assessment Program summer bottom trawl survey data from 1990 to 2025. Colors denote NMFS statistical areas.</figureCaption>
	</fig>
</figures>
