<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<header>
	<docType>ESR Contribution</docType>
	<indicatorShortName>forage_fish</indicatorShortName>
	<indicatorTitle>Fisheries-independent Survey-based Indices of Forage Fishes in the Gulf of Alaska</indicatorTitle>
	<indicatorRegion>GOA</indicatorRegion>
	<authors>Margaret Siple</authors>
	<contactEmail>Margaret.Siple@noaa.gov</contactEmail>
	<authorAffiliations>Resource Assessment and Conservation Engineering Division, Alaska Fisheries Science Center, NOAA Fisheries</authorAffiliations>
	<lastUpdate>March 2025</lastUpdate>
</header>
<body>
	<indicatorDescription>The Resource Assessment and Conservation Engineering Division’s Groundfish Assessment Program (RACE-GAP) fishery-independent summer bottom trawl surveys in the Gulf of Alaska (GOA) are designed to assess populations of commercially and ecologically important fishes and invertebrates. Since 1990, we have deployed the same standardized trawl gear (footrope and trawl net) as is presently in use in the GOA bottom trawl survey. The North Pacific Fishery Management Council has identified several forage fish species or groups of species for federal management. The survey catches Pacific sandlance, eulachon, capelin, sandfish, and pricklebacks though the trawl mesh size is sufficiently large to allow escapement for most of these species. Because of the highly variable design-based biomass estimates from the trawl survey, the biomass of each forage fish was log-transformed to better show trends. For each species or species group, the largest log-transformed biomass estimate over the time series was arbitrarily scaled to a value of 100 and all other values were scaled in reference to that. The standard error (± 1) was weighted proportionally to the biomass to get a relative standard error.</indicatorDescription>
	<methodologicalChanges>
	Methods for producing this indicator have been updated this year to account for process error in survey abundance estimates, facilitate interpretation of indicator trends, utilize consistent statistical methods across ESR regions, and ensure consistent species group composition across regions. Previously, two time series were presented for each species group: (1) average bottom trawl survey catch-per-unit effort for within INPFC subareas (CPUE, kg ha) that were scaled proportionally to the maximum CPUE in the bottom trawl survey time series, and (2) frequency of occurrence of each species group among bottom trawl survey hauls within INPFC subareas.

This year, we estimated the index of abundance time series by fitting a multivariate random effects model (REM) to INPFC subarea biomass estimates and CVs using the R package rema (Sullivan and Balstad, 2022; Sullivan et al., 2022) to account for process error in indicator time series. Subarea biomass estimates were calculated using the gapindex R package (Oyafuso, 2024), which uses the Wakabayashi et al. (1985) method to estimate design-based indices of abundance from catch (kg) and effort data (area swept; ha) collected during Aleutian Islands summer bottom trawl surveys. The code and methods to calculate abundance indices and fit REM to time series are implemented in the R package esrindex (Rohan, 2024).

Switching to REM addresses an issue raised in conversation during the November 2023 BSAI Groundfish Plan Team meeting pertaining to Structural Epifauna trends in the EBS:

“The Team had a conversation about utilizing random effects models to deal with process error in the indicator and standardizing the index for variables such as bottom contact time.”

We note that bottom contact time is already accounted for in bottom trawl survey effort data because effort is only calculated for the time the net is on bottom based on bottom contact sensor data.

	</methodologicalChanges>
	<statusAndTrends>The biomass of forage fishes in the GOA is difficult to measure in NOAA Fisheries’ bottom trawl survey catches due to issues such as gear selectivity and catchability. Therefore, we anticipate that the relative biomass estimates presented here for forage fishes are imprecise so that apparent trends should be interpreted cautiously. Eulachon have been most prevalent in the Yakutat survey district though their greatest biomass has historically occurred in the Kodiak district where biomass appears to be increasing in recent surveys after highs recorded between 2000 and 2015 (Figure 57). Capelin biomass has historically been highest in the Kodiak district. Sandfish, prickelbacks, and sand lance are uniformly uncommon in trawl catches across the GOA survey years and districts, though there are episodic years with large biomass estimates for these species over the survey history.</statusAndTrends>
	<factorsInfluencingTrends>Unknown</factorsInfluencingTrends>
	<implications>The NOAA Fisheries’ survey trawl gear has catchability and selectivity issues for forage fishes that impact their catch and retention. Therefore, relative biomass estimates for these species are of limited value for interpreting long-term abundance trends or population status.</implications>
	<researchPriorities>NA</researchPriorities>
</body>
<figures>
	<fig>
		<figureNumber>1</figureNumber>
		<figurePath>GOA_rema_forage_fish_full_region_ze.png</figurePath>
		<figureCaption>Biomass index of Forage Fish (Pacific herring, capelin, eualchon, sandlances, myctophids, Pacific sandfish, pricklebacks) from AFSC/RACE summer bottom trawl surveys of the Gulf of Alaska from 1990 to 2023. Panels show  showing the observed survey biomass index mean (blue points), random effects model fitted mean (solid black line), 95% confidence interval (gray shading), overall time series mean (solid gray line), and horizontal dashed gray lines representing one standard deviation from the mean.</figureCaption>
	</fig>
	<fig>
		<figureNumber>2</figureNumber>
		<figurePath>GOA_rema_forage_fish_subarea_bar.png</figurePath>
		<figureCaption>Biomass index of Forage Fish (Pacific herring, capelin, eualchon, sandlances, myctophids, Pacific sandfish, pricklebacks) in the Gulf of Alaska estimated from AFSC/RACE summer bottom trawl survey data from 1990 to 2023.</figureCaption>
	</fig>
</figures>
